A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10 FA282
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
1927-1949
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA282
1.76 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Scope and Contents note
The work of the Division on Community Clinics continued the efforts of Division II of the Program for the Prevention of Delinquency. Division II began its first demonstration child guidance clinic at St. Louis on May 10, 1922. With the expiration of the CF's five year program, the Cleveland Clinic's (December 31, 1926) and the Philadelphia Clinic's (June 30, 1927), demonstration nature ended, and they became permanent independent bodies. The entire Division II program was revised to stress increased use of the supervisory and consulting functions of the Division's field consultant staff, and promoted 1) continued contact with and supervision of the permanent clinics, and 2) additional field service to cities requesting assistance and advice regarding mental hygiene problems and programs.
The first director for the new division was George S. Stevenson, and Clara Bassett, the former chief social worker of the Vanderbilt Clinic, became the consultant in psychiatric social work. The Commonwealth Fund continued to support the National Committee for Mental Hygiene and its Division on Community Clinics until 1949. The last appropriation, $2,000, was voted June 16, 1949, for the 1949-1950 fiscal year.
Existing documentation from the Division on Community Clinics consists of Dr. Stevenson's extensive correspondence with Commonwealth Fund officers and many state or local health officials. Some of the correspondence files may include internal memoranda, which are also filed separately, and field reports. Financial records for the Division are quite complete, and comprise budget and fiscal statements as well as correspondence relating to Division expenditures. The quarterly reports filed by Dr. Stevenson with the Commonwealth Fund provide comprehensive insight into the administrative decisions affecting the Division and the field and clinical work being performed by the organization.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Public welfare; United States; War relief; New York (State); Public health; Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); Child welfare; Child psychology; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Legal issues; Law; Medical education; Legal research; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Social Science Research Council; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Columbia University; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Harvard University; Yale University; Harkness, Charles W.
- Assistance to Clinics - Charleston, South Carolina Mental Hygiene Clinic, December 19, 1929-May 27, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Assistance to Clinics - Declinations (B-P), 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Assistance to Clinics - Declinations (R-W), 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Assistance to Clinics - Houston, Texas Child Guidance Clinic, November 18, 1930-December 12, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Assistance to Clinics - Louisville, Kentucky Psychological Clinic, July 10, 1930-July 3, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Assistance to Clinics - Portland, Oregon Child Guidance Clinic, May 13, 1930-November 8, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Assistance to Clinics - Virginia State Clinic, March 12, 1928-January 31, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Child Guidance Clinic - Cleveland, Ohio, January 13, 1927-May 7, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Child Guidance Clinic - Dallas, Texas, December 5, 1924-May 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Child Guidance Clinic - Memphis, Tennessee, April 16, 1924-May 1, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Child Guidance Clinic - Minneapolis, Minnesota, October 13, 1924-February 11, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted - Confidential material. Requires prior archival review.
- Child Guidance Clinic - St. Louis, Missouri, March 15, 1924-June 21, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Child Guidance Clinic - St. Paul, Minnesota, February 3, 1927-January 12, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Comparative Study of Child Guidance Clinic Monthly Report Figures, January 1929-June 1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Conference on Cooperative Work, March 27-30, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Conference on Evaluation of Case Work Progress, November 1, 1929-May 8, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, February 14, 1927-December 18, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, February 14, 1927-December 18, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, February 14, 1927-December 18, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, February 14, 1927-December 18, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, February 14, 1927-December 18, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, January 2, 1931-December 6, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, August 17, 1927-December 30, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, January 3, 1940-July 5, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, January 3, 1940-July 5, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, January 3, 1940-July 5, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, January 3, 1940-July 5, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Financial Data and Correspondence, January 3, 1940-July 5, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Inter-office Conference Memoranda, January 3, 1929-June 9, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Inter-office Conference Memoranda, January 3, 1929-June 9, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Inter-office Conference Memoranda, January 3, 1929-June 9, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Quarterly Reports, October 1, 1927-December 31, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 60)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 61)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 62)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 64)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 65)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 66)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 67)
- Quarterly Reports, January 1, 1934-August 1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 68)
- Study of Mental Hygiene Clinic Boards, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Survey Report - Delaware State Hospital, September 1931 (Box 4, Folder 70)
- Survey Report - Mental Hygiene Survey Committee of Scranton, Pennsylvania, May 1931 (Box 4, Folder 71)